<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the publicke fast To the Commons house of Parliament. April. 5th. 1628. By Ier. Dyke minister of Gods Word, at Epping in Essex.</title>
            <author>Dyke, Jeremiah, 1584-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100103</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835955</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21056)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 1064:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the publicke fast To the Commons house of Parliament. April. 5th. 1628. By Ier. Dyke minister of Gods Word, at Epping in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Dyke, Jeremiah, 1584-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 49, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Nicholas Okes] for Robert Mylbourne, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church yard, at the signe of the Gray-Hound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Hebrews XI, 7.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-G⁴ H² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:190:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT the Publicke Faſt. TO The Commons Houſe of Parliament. APRIL. 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1628.</p>
            <p>By IER. DYKE Miniſter of GODS Word, at <hi>Epping</hi> in ESSEX.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ROM. 13. 11.</bibl>
               <p>And that knowing the time, that now it is high time to awake out of ſleepe.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obticeſcant ergo linguae dioentium, manducemus et bibamus, cras enim moriemur. Prorſus et vos reſpondete, et dicite. Ieiunemus &amp; oremus cras enim moriemur.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Aug de Diuerſis. Serm. 120.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui aut abundantia nimia, aut ſecuritate vitiantur deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt eſſe perditi, cum deſtiterint eſſe ſecuri.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Salu. de prouid. lib 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for ROBERT MYLBOVRNE, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Church yard, at the ſigne of the Gray Hound. 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:190:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:190:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE Aſſembly of the Commons Houſe of Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know my ſelfe and mine owne vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe too well, to be ſo far in loue with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of mine own, as to thinke it worthy publicke view. That which once <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpake of himſelfe in humility, I muſt ſay
<pb facs="tcp:190:3"/> of my ſelfe in truth: <note place="margin">Serm. de Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſis. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Quis ſum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go? Homo ſum vnus de multis, non de magnis.</hi> And I know the truth of <hi>Saluians</hi> obſeruation. <note place="margin">Contra. Auarit. lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia dicta tanti exiſtimantur quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt ipſe qui dixit, et qui legunt non tam conſiderant quid legant quam cuius legant, nec tam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis vim atque virtutem quam dictatoris cogitant dignitatem.</hi> So that vpon theſe grounds I had great reaſon to haue for-borne the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of this Sermon. Yet agayne, ſome reaſons there were that were preualent with me, to put it forth. Firſt, that I might a little inlarge ſome things that ſtreights of time would not in the deliuery, permit to be medled withall. Secondly, it was my deſire to leaue a Monument,
<pb facs="tcp:190:3"/> and to giue a publicke teſtimony of my thankefulnes to the Honourable Houſe, for your ſo faire acceptance, and recompence of ſo weake, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy a Seruice, as was done you in this Sermon. Laſtly, endeauours in this kinde haue a bleſſing from God, and want not their ſucceſſe: I eaſily fore-ſee to how many cenſures I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my ſelfe by this courſe, but I haue ſet vp my reſt with him. <note place="margin">Saluian. contr. Auarit. lib. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt nobis in hac parte ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſenſus et Iudicia, quibus idem ſentientibus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nos certi profecto ſumus Deum ipſum ſentire nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum: Pravorum hominum ſenſus aut parvi aeſtimandi ſunt, aut nihil omnino faciendi.</hi> If I find acceptance with thoſe that be good, and hereby may doe any good, I haue enough.
<pb facs="tcp:190:4"/> The God of Heauen guide and bleſſe you in all your weighty deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berations, and make you an happy healing Parliament, to make vp all the breaches of the Land.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours humbly devoted. IER. DYKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:190:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>HEB. 11. 7.</bibl>
                  <p>By Faith <hi>Noah</hi> being warned of God of things not ſeene as yet, moved with feare, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an Arke, to the ſaving of his Houſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the latter end of the former Chapter, the Apoſtle had exhorted vnto perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in the faith. To preſſe this home the better, he ſhewes the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the grace of Faith.</p>
            <p>That he ſhewes
<list>
                  <item>1. By the <hi>excellency</hi> of it, in it ſelfe conſidered. Verſ. 1, 2, 3.</item>
                  <item>2. By a <hi>Cloud of witneſſes,</hi> by the examples of all their fore-fathers in both the Worlds, the World before, and after the Flood.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By all thoſe examples giuing them to vnderſtand that all the goodly things that their Fathers had, or did, they were beholding vnto faith for them. It is the Apoſtles purpoſe in this Chapter to ſet the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land vpon the head of faith, and for the making of this garland, he picks and gathers all the moſt choyce and godly flowers that growe ſcattered through the garden of the Scriptures, and ſo crownes Faith
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:190:5"/> therewith, to make it a louely, and an amiable grace in the eyes of all.</p>
            <p>This ſeauenth verſe contaynes the example of the Faith of <hi>Noah,</hi> who was the laſt Patriarch of the old, and the firſt of the new World. In the verſe we haue conſiderable, two ſpeciall things.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Gods</hi> gracious <hi>goodneſſe</hi> and mercy to <hi>Noah,</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>In giuing warning.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Being warned of God.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Noahs</hi> great <hi>wiſedome</hi> in taking warning.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This wiſedome of his is ſet forth in three degrees,
<list>
                  <item>1. He <hi>beleeues</hi> the warning giuen him. <hi>By</hi> Faith <hi>being warned,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>2. He feares it: <hi>Moued with feare.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. He <hi>makes good vſe</hi> of the warning, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon followes the Counſell of <hi>God.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>God</hi> did not only giue him warning of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but gaue him alſo counſell, and direction, how to ſecure himſelfe from the danger, and he taking the fayre warning, takes alſo the good counſell, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares an Arke: And all theſe be three degrees of one and the ſame thing, each iſſuing and flowing out of other. <hi>God</hi> giues warning therefore. 1. He <hi>beleeues.</hi> 2. His <hi>faith,</hi> breedes <hi>feare</hi> of the calamity approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 3. His <hi>feare</hi> breeds a <hi>care</hi> of the preſeruation of himſelfe, and family. Why builds he an Arke to ſaue his houſe? Becauſe he <hi>feared:</hi> Why doth hee feare? Becauſe hee <hi>beleeues Gods</hi> warning: <hi>God warnes</hi> him, therefore he <hi>beleeues:</hi> He <hi>beleeues</hi> therefore he <hi>feares:</hi> He <hi>feares</hi> therefore hee <hi>prouides</hi> agaynſt a rainy day, and takes a courſe to hide himſelfe, and his family in the day of wrath. For the firſt: <hi>Gods</hi> mercy and goodneſſe to <hi>Noah. Being warned of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:190:5"/>
            <p>The old World was growne to an horrible hight of iniquity. The Children of <hi>God,</hi> the poſterity of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> made mongrell matches with the daughters of men, the poſterity of <hi>Caine.</hi> Thoſe mongrell mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches brought forth a monſtrous brood, who defiled, and polluted the very earth. <hi>God</hi> ſaw the earth ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with their villanies, that he determines to bring ſuch a iudgement vpon the earth, as ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſweepe thoſe monſters from off the earth, but ſuch an one as ſhould lay the earth a ſoake, and ſhould waſh and wrince it from the filth and defilement where-with they had corrupted it. <hi>God</hi> hauing ſet downe this determination, he doth not preſently put it in execution; but firſt acquaints <hi>Noah</hi> with his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and giues him warning of it, and that to this end, that he might giue the world warning. For as <hi>God</hi> by immediate reuelation, gaue <hi>Noah</hi> warning; ſo <hi>Noah</hi> by preparing the Arke, gaue the World war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a iudgment comming, and that vnleſſe ſome courſe was taken to preuent it, they were all in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to bee ſwept away with a Flood; from which courſe of <hi>Gods:</hi> Learne.</p>
            <p>Gods faire dealing in the adminiſtration, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of Iuſtice: Seldome or neuer doth <hi>God</hi> bring generall iudgements vpon a people, but he giues them faire warning. Hee doth not ſtrike men at vnawares, and ſuddainly ſurpriſe them, without any notice gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of his purpoſes. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33. 3. <hi>When the ſword comes vppon the Land, hee muſt blow the Trumpet, and</hi> warne <hi>the people.</hi> The Prophet <hi>verſe</hi> 7. <hi>Muſt heare the Word at Gods mouth, and</hi> warne <hi>them from him.</hi> Yea, ſo carefull is God that it be done, that if in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:190:6"/> caſe it be neglected, he threatens to reckon ſharply with thoſe whom hee betruſts with that office, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. God will require <hi>blood</hi> at ſuch mens hands. God doth not ſnatch vp the ſword into his hand, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut men of; but <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 12. Firſt, God <hi>whets his ſword, bends his bow, makes it ready; prepares the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of death.</hi> And all this whetting time, the time of making ready, and preparing, is a warning time. God whets, and makes ready in mens ſight, and in mens hearing, that the very noyſe of his whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, may giue them warning of his intentions. And <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 41, 42. God firſt <hi>Whets his Sword before it devoures fleſh;</hi> and God firſt <hi>takes hold on iudgement,</hi> before his judgements take hold on men.</p>
            <p>God liu'd by his owne rule, and by the ſame Law, he gaue his people in their warres. <hi>Deuter.</hi> 20. 10. 13. Hee would not haue them fall foule preſently vppon their enemies, but they muſt deale fairely with them. And it was the benefit of this Law, that the wiſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Abel</hi> challenged at the hands of <hi>Ioab,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 18. and blames him that hee was come to <hi>ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp,</hi> and neuer according to the ancient Law of Armes giues them any parley, or warning of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. So fairely deales God in his infinite goodneſſe with men, before hee comes to ſwallow vp, and to deſtroy; hee firſt giues warning, and offers fayre quarter. Therefore, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5. 8. God <hi>blowes the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet</hi> before he drawes the ſword; not a Trumpet for an Alarme, and for the battle; but a Trumpet to giue warning that a battle is like to come. God hath his warning peeces; and his murdering peeces: God neuer diſchargeth his murdering, till hee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:190:6"/> haue diſcharged his Warning ones.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Syria</hi> his plot and policy, was ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and at unawares, to ſurpriſe the King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 6. 8. He would go covertly, and cloſly to work leaſt the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> having intelligence of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, he might thereby fruſtrate his action. God goes not ſo covertly to worke, but as one that would be willing to be kept off, and put by, he himſelfe giues intelligence of his intentions, hee doth afore-hand acquaint men with his projects. <hi>Ier.</hi> 18. 11, <hi>Behold I frame evill againſt you, and deviſe a device againſt you. Thus God deales, and giues warning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That if it be poſſible, men might bee brought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Repentance, as might prevent the threatned e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ier.</hi> 18. 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he may provide for the good of his owne. Sometimes God will deliver ſome of his people from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> calamity. Sometimes he will haue ſome of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>dergo it. In reference to both, he giues warning.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſuch as ſhall be delivered in the day of wrath: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wrath ſhould come without warning, it might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>de of Gods owne people, from vnder couert, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they might prooue a prey to the judgement. <hi>Exod.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. 18, 19. God had a purpoſe that many of the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> ſervants and Cattle ſhould eſcape, and not bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ayne, in that terrible ſtorme of fire and hayle. God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>erefore giues warning of the ſtorme, that ſo they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ight be houſed that ſhould eſcape. If they had had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> warning, they had heene abroad in the fields; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the fields when the ſtorme came, they had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ht inevitably. God hath a purpoſe in a ſtorme to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome of his, therefore hee giues them warning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:190:7"/> that they may get an houſe ouer their heads before the ſtorme come. What had <hi>Noah</hi> beene better then all the reſt of the vngodly World, if God had not giuen him warning: <hi>God</hi> warned him that hee might be ſafe in the evill day. When iudgements come, and are walking abroad, <hi>God</hi> would haue his people within doores, in their Chambers, their doores ſhut vpon them. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 26. 20, 21. and therefore to this end giues them warning. 2. In reference to ſuch as ſhall vndergoe common calamity, <hi>God</hi> giues them warning that they may lay in, and lay vp that which may ſupport and vphold them in the time of diſtreſſe. <hi>God</hi> would haue the demeaner and behauiour of his people in the day of calamity be different from other mens. He would haue them be of erected ſpirits, free from thoſe diſtreſſing perplexities, that others ſhalbe ſwallowed vp withall. Therefore hee giues warning that ſo they may gather that which may ſtrengthen them at ſuch a time: certainely if <hi>God</hi> ſhould giue no warning, there would bee little difference ſeene and diſcerned betweene the <hi>righteous, and the wicked; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene him that ſerueth God, and him that ſerues him not. Mal.</hi> 3. 18. Little difference would bee ſeene in their carriages vnder the preſſures of calamity: You ſhould ſee <hi>Euery man with his hands on his loynes, as a Woman in trauaile, and all faces turned into pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse. Ier.</hi> 30. 6. <hi>God</hi> would haue his people haue more blood in their faces, then the common ſort wil haue in ſuch a time. <hi>God</hi> would not haue Faith and Religion ſo pale faced, and ſo white liuer'd, as ciuility, and morality, will be at ſuch a time. Therefore <hi>God</hi> giues them warning, that ſo their prouiſions may be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:190:7"/> ſuch agaynſt the day of euill; as that their carriages may be maſculine, beſeeming <hi>God</hi> and Religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>God</hi> may be iuſtified, and cleare, when he iudges. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 4. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Talis non vis flagellari cum mundo, aut fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellatus mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muras ſub fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gello? Serue male, feciſti quod Dominus iuſſit, qui ne vapulares, iſta flagella ante tibi praedixit? August. de tem. Barb.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>God</hi> doth it to gag, and to muzzle the mouth of iniquity; and to put to ſilence the cauelling ignorance of fooliſh men. What can be pleaded agaynſt the iuſtice of <hi>Gods</hi> proceedings, when <hi>God</hi> may ſay to men, as <hi>Reuben</hi> to his brethren. <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. 22. <hi>Did not I warne you, ſaying, ſin not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> How doth God giue warning of wrath, and iudgements comming?</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1.</label> 
               <hi>God</hi> giues warning many wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By extraordinary, and immediate Reuelation. Thus was <hi>Noah</hi> heere warned of God, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The ſame word that is vſed of the warning giuen to the wiſemen <hi>Math.</hi> 2. 12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, warned of God. <hi>God</hi> in a dreame immediately warned them. And thus were all the Prophets warned of <hi>God,</hi> of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that were to come vpon the Iewes, and other Nations. And thus ſpecially is that to be vnderſtood. <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 7. <hi>Surely the Lord God will doe nothing, but he reueales his ſecrets vnto his ſeruants the Prophets.</hi> God by the extraordinary reuelation of his ſpirit, gaue them warning what hee meant to doe. Thus God made knowne to <hi>Nebucadnezar</hi> what ſhould come to paſſe afterwards. <hi>Daniel</hi> 2. 29.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By prodigious ſignes, and ſtrange wonders, both in Heauen and earth. <hi>God</hi> calls his worke of iudgement, <hi>a ſtrange worke;</hi> and <hi>a strange act. Iſa.</hi> 28. 21. And when <hi>God</hi> doth theſe <hi>strange acts,</hi> and workes of nationall iudgements, hee giues warnings many times thereof by ſome ſtrange precurſory ſignes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:190:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:190:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:190:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:190:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:190:10"/> and prodigies: Commonly ſome ſtrange praemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſignes fore runne, ſtrange executions of iuſtice: We haue a text for it. <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 11. <hi>Great earthquakes ſhalbe in diuerſe places, and famines, and pestilences, and fearefull fights; and great ſignes ſhall there bee from Heauen:</hi> And ſo it came to paſſe before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by a prodigious comet, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fearefull ſights <hi>God</hi> gaue them warning of their approaching ruine.</p>
            <p>Wee ſhall ſeldome finde any calamitous time to haue befallen this kingdome which hath not had a fore-warning giuen of it by ſome prodigious things ſuch as was the rayning of blood at Yorke, ſometime before the Danes entrance into the Land, and others many of the like nature, as they know well that are but any thing ſeene into our Chronicles. And what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience can it be to coniecture, that God by that prodigious blazing Starre, <hi>Anno</hi> 1618. gaue the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches warning of the heavie and lamentable times that haue ſince enſued, &amp; yet happily are to enſue. God had a <hi>ſtrange worke,</hi> and a <hi>ſtrange act,</hi> to doe, and he gaue warning of it by as ſtrange a blazing Starre as had bin ſeene in many ages. God ſpeakes by all ſuch ſignes, and therefore wee reade of the <hi>words</hi> of Gods <hi>ſignes and wonders, Pſal.</hi> 105. 27. ſo the words are ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally. And ſo of the <hi>voyce</hi> of his ſignes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>If they will not hearken to the voyce of the firſt ſigne.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods ſignes haue <hi>wordes,</hi> haue a <hi>voyce</hi> they ſpeake not onely to our eyes, but to our eares alſo. They are not onely to be gazed upon, but to bee hearkened to, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 7. <hi>Our fathers</hi> vnderſtood <hi>not thy wonders in Egypt,</hi> Gods wonders then haue a language, and they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:190:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> are not onely to bee lookt vppon, but their language muſt be vnderſtood. Now their words are Monitory words, their language is a Monitory language, and they giue vs warning that ſome great iudgements are at hand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God giues warning by the Miniſtery of the word. Though Gods miniſters haue not an Oraculous war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by Immediate Revelation; yet they may ſee an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill in the cauſes, as a ſtorme in the black cloudes, and by conſidering, and comparing things preſent, with things paſt, and looking into Gods ancient wayes may ſee in the general that miſchiefe is comming, and ſo from God giue warning. <hi>Eliſha</hi> hath his ſword as well as <hi>Iehu,</hi> and <hi>Hazael.</hi> 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19. 17. And when <hi>Eliſha</hi> vnſheathes and brandiſhes his ſword, it is a faire war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that the ſword of <hi>Iehu,</hi> and <hi>Hazael</hi> are at hand. <hi>God cuts downe by his Prophets, and ſlayes by the wordes of his mouth. Hoſe.</hi> 6. 5. before hee bringes in enemyes to kill and ſlay, and when his Miniſters are killing and ſlaying it is a warning ſigne that enemyes ſhall come to doe the like. So Ieremy <hi>rootes out, pulles downe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes, and throwes downe Kingdomes. Ier.</hi> 1. 10. And when Ieremy begins to plucke vp &amp; deſtroy, it is an ill ſigne that Babilonians, and other nations are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming at hand to doe the ſame worke. Whatſoeuer ye bind on earth ſhalbe bound in heauen; and ſo whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yee roote out on earth ſhalbe rooted out in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; is not onely true of an extraordinary and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Miniſtry, but of the ordinary ſtanding miniſtry of the Church, when Miniſters go to worke <hi>Claue non erante,</hi> and follow the rules and grounds of the word. The watchman giues warning. <hi>Eze.</hi> 33. 3. but how? <hi>if</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:190:11"/> 
               <hi>he blow the trumpet, and giue warning.</hi> When Gods watchmen blow the trumpet, then God giues war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Specially then are the warnings of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to be taken as warnings from God, when God ſhal ſtirre vp the harts of his ſeruants euery where in all parts, &amp; places of a kingdome far diſtant, and remote each from other, to giue warning to a Kingdome. That looke as it is an argument of the diuine authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of prophetical Scripture, that the Prophets though they liued in diuerſe places and ages of the world, yet they ſo al agreed in one &amp; the ſame truth as if they had all ſpoken by one mouth. <hi>Hence Luke.</hi> 1. 70. <hi>As he ſpake by the mouth of his holy Prophets.</hi> There were many <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> yet but one <hi>mouth,</hi> they all ſo agreed that though there were diverſe perſons, yet but one mouth, <hi>as hee ſpake by the mouth,</hi> not the mouthes of his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>which haue beene ſince the world began.</hi> So here, when God doth ſtirre vp his ſeruants in all parts of a kingdome, and ſets them all on worke as with one mouth to giue warning of wrath, it may be taken for no leſſe then a diuine warning from God himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="4">4 God giues warning by his adminiſtration, and dealing with other nations, and Churches. Gods rods are not only ſmarting rods to them vpon whom they are, but they are monitory &amp; <hi>warning</hi> rods to thoſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as yet they are not. <hi>Zep.</hi> 3. 6. 7. <hi>I haue cut off nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I haue made their ſtreets waſt, &amp;c.</hi> what was one end God had in it? To giue Ieruſalem warning. <hi>I ſaid, ſurely thou wilt feare me, thou wilt receiue instruction, ſo their dwellings ſhould not be cut off.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oportet abie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vlulare quia cecidit Cedrus, ac ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os vicinorum plaga erudiri atque per ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ena mala re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuis probe conſulere. Greg. Naz.</hi>
               </note> God then aimed at this in his Iudgements vpon other nations that Ieruſalem ſhould take warning. Then <hi>God</hi> giues warning whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:190:11"/> puts the ſword into Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion. It is warning when he whets his ſword, but much more when he giues the ſword a Commiſſion. <hi>Ezekel.</hi> 14. 17. <hi>If I ſay; Sword goe through a land, ſo that I cut off man and beaſt from it.</hi> There is the ſword put in Commiſſion, and being ſo put in Commiſſion, there is warning giuen of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching calamitie. We may know the ſword to be in Commiſſion as wee know the Iudges of Aſſize to bee. When we ſee the Iudges ride circuite, and goe from one ſhire towne to another, and doe executions vppon malefactors: then wee know they haue their Commiſſions: Iudges may not ride circuit without their Commiſſions. So when wee ſee the ſword ride circuit, and doe Executions euery where as it goes, and cannot bee ſtaide, but it proſpers and preuailes, then without all queſtion it is in Commiſſion. When it goes through Lands, and Prouinces, and Churches, and cuts off man and beaſt, then queſtionleſſe God hath ſaid, <hi>Sword, Go.</hi> See <hi>Ier.</hi> 47. 6, 7. <hi>Oh thou ſword of the Lord, how long will it be ere thou bee quiet: put vp thy ſelfe into thy ſcabberd, reſt and be ſtill.</hi> Like inough <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelon,</hi> and the Philiſtins vſed all the policie, and power they could: but all their Combinations, Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Leagues, Vnions, could do no good. For all theſe the ſword was reſtleſſe, and proſpered ſtrangely, and not by any weakeneſſe of theirs, nor by any ſtrength of the enemy the victory ſtill loſt: ſo as a diuine hand of God was manifeſt therein. What might the reaſon of all this be? It had a charge: <hi>How can it be quiet, ſeeing the Lord hath giuen it a charge againſt Aſhkelon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the ſword hath a Commiſſion, it doth as <hi>Samuel</hi> did, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 16. <hi>He went from yeare to yeare in</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:190:12"/> 
               <hi>circuit to Bethel, and Gilgal and Mizpeh, and iudged Iſrael in all thoſe places, and his returne was to Ramah.</hi> Now looke then, as when <hi>Samuel</hi> was at <hi>Bethel,</hi> then they had warning that hee was comming to <hi>Gilgal,</hi> when he was at <hi>Gilgal</hi> then had they warning that hee was comming to do Iudgment at <hi>Mizpeh:</hi> So when the ſword is once walking circuit to iudge, if it bee come to <hi>Bethel,</hi> it is a warning that it is comming to <hi>Gilgal,</hi> if at <hi>Gilgal,</hi> there is a warning for <hi>Mizpeh.</hi> Let other Kingdomes, and Churches, that ſtands by and looke on, let them take this as a warning from God, that the ſword is comming to execute iudgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. Then it is a warning that God will giue men to the ſword: <hi>when euill goes forth from nation to nation, Ier.</hi> 25. 32. And why ſhould other nations bee amazed, and their Kings be horribly afraid, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble euery man for his owne life in the day of Egypts fall by the ſword, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 32. 10. were it not but that Gods dealing with Egypt, were a warning of the like wrath, and ruine comming vppon themſelues?</p>
            <p n="5">5 God giues warning by doing, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 50. <hi>He made a way to his anger,</hi> he <hi>gaue their life ouer to the peſtilence.</hi> God brought the peſtilence amongſt them, but yet firſt he made a way for his anger, and his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a way, was a warning that wrath was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. God when he meanes that wrath ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: hee doth not preſently let it breake in; but firſt <hi>makes a way</hi> for it, takes all things out of the way, that may ſtop or hinder it in its paſſage, or be any rub to it in its entrance. Now then when we ſee God prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and <hi>making the way,</hi> then hee giues warning of wrath comming, and being at hand. When Chriſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:190:12"/> was to manifeſt himſelfe in his miniſterie, firſt <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> muſt come before him, and his office was, <hi>Mark.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>To prepare the way of the Lord.</hi> Now then thoſe that had eyes to ſee <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> preparing a way for Chriſt, might eaſily ſee that God gaue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that Chriſt himſelfe was ſhortly to come: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Iohn was <hi>preparing a way</hi> for him. So when God is preparing a way for wrath, ſuch as haue eyes to ſee the way preparing, may ſee God giuing warning, that ſome heauie iudgement and calamitie is at hand. When the Kings harbengers come before, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for the King, it is a warning to ſuch places that the King is comming. God ſo deales in the bringing in of iudgements vpon a nation, as he did in bringing in that great plague vppon the Church, in bringing in Antichriſt into the world, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>The miſtery of iniquitie doth already worke, onely hee who letteth will let, vntill he be taken out of the way.</hi> That plague was breeding long before it brake forth and came to ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but there was a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; namely, the Romane Ethnick Emperours that ſtood in the way, and till they were firſt done out of the way, the man of ſinne could not enter: but when that let ſhould be taken out of the way, and ſo a way made, <hi>Then ſhall that wicked one be reuealed, v.</hi> 8. So that when that let was done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and ſo a way making, ſuch as had then eyes to ſee it, might ſee that God gaue warning that Antichriſt was now comming into the world. So it is in this caſe, Iudgement is breeding long before it comes. God hath a purpoſe to bring it, but yet many times there bee ſome lets in the way that it cannot well come till they bee remoued; God therefore prepares, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:190:13"/> makes a way for the intended Iudgement by remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and taking out of the way euery <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry let that may hinder it when it comes. And when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he way is making, God giues warning that the Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is comming. Now God commonly makes the way by two things; The <hi>Moath</hi> and the <hi>Hornet.</hi> And when thoſe two come then are the harbengers come, and the Iohn Baptiſts of the Iudgement.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>Moath,</hi> when God meanes to bring a Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon a Kingdome hee firſt giues warning by making way for it by the <hi>Moath.</hi> God threatens, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5. 14. a terrible Iudgment that hee will be to <hi>Ephraim as a Lyon, and as a young Lyon to the Houſe of Iudah, that hee will teare and goe away, &amp;c.</hi> But will God giue no warning, yes that he will, and faire warning too. And how? <hi>By making way,</hi> for the Lyon by the moath v. 12. <hi>I will bee vnto Ephraim</hi> as a moath, <hi>and to the Houſe of Iudah as rottenneſſe.</hi> The <hi>moath</hi> is a ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible Iudgment that gradually, and inſenſibly eates out the heart and ſtrength of a State, and by the weakning of a State prepares it for a fatall deſolatory Iudgment.</p>
            <p>A <hi>moath</hi> eates now one threed, then another, makes now one hole, then another, and ſo by degrees wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and rotting the garment perpares it with much eaſe, to be rent in pieces. It is difficult to rende in pieces a ſtrong ſound garment, but when once it is all moath eaten, and rotten, how eaſy is it for any: much more for a Lion to rende it: thus therefore would God prepare Ephraim for the <hi>Lion</hi> by the <hi>moath,</hi> and by the <hi>moath</hi> giue him warning of the <hi>Lion.</hi> VVhat this <hi>moath</hi> is wee may ſee plainely by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:190:13"/> that, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 3. 1. 2. 3. with the eight verſe. In the eight verſe, God threatens the <hi>ruine and the fall of Iudah and Ieruſalem.</hi> But wil God come ſuddainly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them? No, hee will giue them faire warning: But how? By making way for their fatall blow, and for the <hi>Lions</hi> clawes by the teeth of the <hi>moath.</hi> Firſt before the <hi>Lion</hi> comes they ſhal ſee a way making for him by the <hi>moath. ver.</hi> 1. 2. 3. <hi>for the Lord of hoaſt doth take away from Ieruſalem, and from Iudah the ſtay and the ſtaffe.</hi> Firſt God before he ruines them will weaken them, and by ſome precurſory Iudgement wil infeeble them by taking from them whatſoeuer might ſtrenghten them againſt an enemy, that when an enemy comes, they ſhal haue no ſtay, nor ſtaffe to reſt vpon againſt him. If an enemy doe offer to make an invaſion; yet if a people be well ſtored with prouiſions, they haue good ſtore of bread, trading be quick, that there be no generall pouerty and penury in the Land, it is a great ſtay againſt an enemy, it is a ſtrong threed in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Againe if an enemy doe attempt an invaſion, yet if the State be wel furniſht with Prudent, Ancient, experienced Counſelors, if withal it be wel prouided of braue ſouldiers, men of war, mighty men, Captaines of fifty, braue Leaders, &amp; Commanders, this is a great ſtay to a State, theſe be ſtrong threeds in the cloth that will not ſuffer it eaſily to be rent. It will bee hard to rend ſuch cloth a ſunder that hath ſuch ſtrong threeds in it; Therefore that it may the eaſier be rent in peices God will ſend ſome Iudgement before hand that moath-like ſhall eate aſunder thoſe threeds, hee will bring in the decay of trading which is the bread of a Land, hee will now take away one Prudent man, then
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:190:14"/> another, now ſuch a man of warre, and then another, and thus by degrees ſo weaken them that when an enemy ſhould come hauing al reſiſtances remoued he may with all caſe ruine Iudah and Ieruſalem. Thus Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah by the <hi>moath</hi> had warning of the <hi>Lyon,</hi> and when God made their State and their Kingdome a motheaten Kingdome, he thereby gaue them warning that they ſhould aſſuredly fall, and ruine.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Hornet.</hi> When God meanes to bring Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon a Kingdome he giues warning thereof by premiſing and fore-ſending, the <hi>hornet. Exod.</hi> 23. 28. I <hi>will ſend Hornets before thee which ſhall driue out the Hiuite, the Canaanite before thee.</hi> What that <hi>Hornet</hi> is wee may ſee <hi>v.</hi> 27. <hi>I will ſend my feare before thee, and will destory all the people to whom thou ſhalt come and I will make all thine enemyes turne their backes vnto thee.</hi> This <hi>Hornet</hi> then was nothing elſe but the miſgiuing feare of the Canaanites ſelfe-condemning conſciences, which ſhould take all heart and courage from them, that they ſhould not be able to ſtand it out in the day of battaile, but their owne guilty conſciences repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting vnto them their deſerts, ſhould <hi>Hornet-</hi>like ſo ſting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with feare, that they ſhould turne their backes to the Iſraelites. And this was that which <hi>Rahab</hi> told the ſpies, and vpon which ſhee concludes that the Land was theirs, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 2. 9. 11. <hi>I know the Lord hath giuen you the land.</hi> How did ſhe know it? ſhe ſaw the <hi>Hornet</hi> was come before, and had ſtung the Canaanites, and thereby gaue warning of ruine, <hi>And that your</hi> terrour is <hi>fallen vpon vs,</hi> and <hi>that all the inhabitants of the land faynt becauſe of you, And as ſoone as we had heard theſe things our hearts did melt, neither did there remayne any</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:190:14"/> 
               <hi>more courage in any man becauſe of you.</hi> Here was the <hi>ſtinge</hi> of the <hi>Hornet,</hi> here was the <hi>Hornet</hi> making way for wrath. If the Canaanites had had courage and ſpirit, and ſhould haue ſtood ſtoutly, and brauely to it, it would not haue been ſo eaſie a matter for <hi>Iſrael</hi> to haue conquered <hi>Canaan,</hi> but now becauſe <hi>God</hi> would ruine the Canaanites, and giue <hi>Iſrael</hi> their land, therefore hee ſends the <hi>Hornet</hi> before to make way for their entrance, and ſo to ſting them that all <hi>Courage,</hi> and <hi>Heart</hi> might bee taken away. And when the Canaanites feele this <hi>ſtinging Hornet,</hi> then haue they plaine warning that their Deſolation is approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. This is that <hi>Hornet</hi> which <hi>God</hi> ſent before the <hi>Medes,</hi> to make way for the deſtruction of the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Eſay.</hi> 13. 7, 8, 9. And this is that <hi>Hornet,</hi> that made way for the <hi>Babylonians</hi> to <hi>ruine Ieruſalem, Ier.</hi> 6. 24. <hi>Wee haue heard the fame thereof, our hands waxe feeble, anguiſh hath taken hold of vs, and paine as of a woman in trauaile.</hi> This was that <hi>Hornet,</hi> that made <hi>Pharaohs armes fall downe, Ezech.</hi> 30. 25. and his <hi>ſword to fall out of his hands, v.</hi> 22. Hee was ſo ſtunge at the heart with the feare of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that he had neither ſtrength to lift vp his arme, nor to hold his ſword in his hand. As the <hi>Moath</hi> takes away all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtayes and helps, ſo the <hi>Hornet</hi> takes away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Spirit, and Courage. And when both theſe are taken away, how faire a way is prepared for an enemy. Where euer then mens hearts melt with the feare of an enemie, from the guilt of ſelfe-condemning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinces, it is a warning from <hi>God,</hi> that wrath is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>God</hi> giues warning by his graduall departure from a Nation and a Church. When <hi>God</hi> meanes that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:190:15"/> Iugdement ſhall come, hee himſelfe will firſt depart, and as Iudgement ſhall come, ſo will he goe. Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes not all at once vppon a nation but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and <hi>God</hi> giues it an admiſſion by a graduall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and departure. Now then whenſoeuer <hi>God</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes to goe, then is it a faire warning that Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is comming. In the ninth, tenth, and eleuenth Chapters of <hi>Ezekiel, God</hi> makes diuers remoues. And we ſhall ſtill obſerue that as hee goes out, ſo ſome new Iudgement comes in. 1. He remoues from the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins, in the Oracle to the threſhold, <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. 3. and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that remoue ſee what followes, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. Hee remoues to the Cherubins on the right ſide of the houſe, <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. 1. and vpon that remoue ſee what followes, <hi>v.</hi> 2. 3. He remoues to the Eaſt gate of the houſe, and the firſt entrance into the Temple, <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. 19. and ſee what followes vppon that, <hi>Cap.</hi> 11. 8, 9, 10. 4. He remoues to Mount Oliuer quite out of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Cap.</hi> 11. 23. And when <hi>God</hi> was gone quite out, then followed the fatall calamity in the ruine therof. Thus ſtill as <hi>God</hi> went out, Iudgement came in, and by theſe ſteps of his departure, hee gaue warning of the comming of Iudgement. When <hi>God</hi> is at the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, Iudgement is at the doores. So <hi>Amos.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>I ſaw the Lord ſtanding vppon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Altar.</hi> But what doth the Lord ſtanding vppon the Altar? His ſtation was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Cherubins in the Holy place: <hi>Giue eare thou that dwellest betweene the Cherubins. Pſal.</hi> 80. 1. What then meanes the Lords ſtanding vpon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar? ſurely it meanes no good. It is a ſigne God was going, he hath made a ſtep from the Cherubins to the Altar, and ſee what followes in that place: namely; a terrible ſentence of Iudgement. <hi>God</hi> is at the Altar
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:190:15"/> when this ſentence is pronounced. It is in this caſe as it was in that. <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. 9, 10. <hi>The anger of the Lord was kindled against them, and he departed.</hi> When <hi>God</hi> is angry, then will he depart. And what if he doe, what wil follow? <hi>And the cloude departed from off the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and behold Miriam became Leprous.</hi> No ſooner doth <hi>God</hi> depart, but Iudgement comes in his roome. So that when <hi>God</hi> beginnes to ſet his firſt foote for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, it is a faire warning of euill comming. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Angells could do nothing to <hi>Sodome,</hi> ſo long as <hi>Lot</hi> was there: neither can deſolatory Iudgements haue power ouer a Nation ſo long as <hi>God</hi> is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly preſent with them. Therefore as when <hi>Lot</hi> went out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> in that day fire and brimeſtone came downe vpon <hi>Sodome,</hi> ſo when <hi>God</hi> once goes, then are calamities ready to crowde in vpon a Nation.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Gods</hi> departure hath certaine foote-ſteps, which are Ominous preſages of ſorrow at hand.</p>
            <p n="1">1 When Idols and Idolatrie enter into a land. When Gods Arke came into Dagons Temple, then Dagon dropt downe, but when Dagon comes into Gods Temple, and riſes and is aduanced there, then God is going. See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. 5. 6. There was an <hi>Image of Iealouſie,</hi> and therefore <hi>God would go farre off from his Sanctuary.</hi> Specially are <hi>Gods</hi> jealous eyes prouoked, when the caſe is as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43. 8. <hi>That but a wall betweene God, and Idols.</hi> Hee likes no ſuch neere neighbours, hee will be gone rather then brooke ſuch neighbourhood. Nay, it is a ſigne that <hi>God</hi> is already in ſome meaſure gone, for had he held his owne ſtation and poſſeſſion, how could they haue entred. Such a ſtep preſages great calamitie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When the miniſterie of a Church, beginnes to grow corrupt and vnfounde in doctrine and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:190:16"/> when Trueth and Holineſſe departs, <hi>God</hi> departs. Hereupon a corrupt miniſtrie made a preſage of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9. 7. <hi>The dayes of viſitation are come, the dayes of recompence are come, Iſrael ſhall know it,</hi> Nay Iſrael may know it before they come: But how? <hi>The Prophet is a foole, the ſpirituall man is mad.</hi> When Prophets, and ſpirituall men once beginne to bee fooles, and to bee mad, to bee out of their ſpirituall wits, and out of the way of truth, then looke for the dayes of viſitation: becauſe when trueth goes, <hi>God</hi> goes, and when he goes no good can come.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is a manifeſt ſtep of <hi>Gods</hi> departure, when it is with a Nation, as it was with <hi>Sampſon. Iudg.</hi> 16. 20. <hi>He wist not that the Lord was</hi> departed <hi>from him.</hi> But <hi>God</hi> was departed from him, and how appeared it? <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>She began to afflict him, &amp; his ſtrength went from him:</hi> he thought he <hi>would do as at other times,</hi> but could not. At other times he brake the greene withes, at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times hee brake new roapes, at other times hee went away with the pin of the beame, at other times hee was ſtill too good for the Philiſtins, but now hee could not doe as at other times. <hi>God</hi> was departed from him, and therevpon followed that miſery, <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>They put out his eyes, they put him in fetters of braſſe, &amp;c. Gods</hi> departure gaue warning of all this ſorrow, and in that his ſtrength went from him, that he could not doe as at other times; this was the impreſſion of <hi>Gods</hi> departing foote. Thus is it with a State and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If <hi>God</hi> depart from them, he thereby giues them warning to looke for Philiſtins, fetters of braſſe, and the priſon houſe. And then may a Nation know that <hi>God</hi> is departing if not departed, when their ſtrength is departed from them, and they cannot doe as they haue done at other times. That ſame is an euident ſtep
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:190:16"/> of <hi>Gods</hi> departure, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 60. 10. <hi>Wilt not thou O God which hadſt caſt vs off? and thou O God which didſt not go out with our armies.</hi> When <hi>God</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goes not forth with a peoples armies, he caſts them off, hee departs from them. And thus <hi>God</hi> departed from Egypt, and gaue them by this ſtep of his departure, warning of their deſtruction. <hi>Ier.</hi> 46. 14. 19. <hi>Standfaſt, prepare thee, for the ſword ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure round about thee, furniſh thy ſelfe to goe into captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> But what ſigne or likelihood of Captiuitie? See <hi>v.</hi> 15. 16. <hi>Why are thy valiant men ſwept away? they ſtoode not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord did driue them; he made many to fal, yea one fell vpon another, &amp; they ſaid: Ariſe, let vs goe againe to our owne people, &amp; to the land of our natiuity from the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſword. God</hi> was departed from them, their enemies beate them, great reaſon hath Egypt to take warning of ſword and Captiuitie comming vpon her: when a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhield is gone, what can they looke for, but to bee bread for their enemies. And thus doth <hi>God</hi> giue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1.</label> Take wee heere notice, of <hi>Gods</hi> gratious dealing with this ſinfull Engliſh nation. Our ſinnes are ſuch, that <hi>God</hi> might haue done with vs, as with <hi>Sodome, Lam.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>That was ouerthrown as in a moment. God</hi> might ſuddenly haue ſurprized vs, &amp; haue let in the flood of his wrath to haue ſwallowed vs vp in a moment. But heere may I ſay as <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 11. 22. <hi>Behold the goodneſſe, and the ſeueritie of God:</hi> The <hi>Seuerity</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in his purpoſes of wrath againſt vs: The <hi>Goodneſse</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in his gratious warnings, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he giues vs intelligence of his Intentions. This day is this trueth fulfilled in our eyes. Wee ſee it true for our parts, that <hi>God</hi> giues faire warnings before Iudgement ceaze vpon a people. <hi>God</hi> neuer gaue any fairer warning then he hath giuen vs: we haue had warnings in all theſe kindes: For,</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:190:17"/>
            <p n="1">1. What if I ſhould ſay that <hi>God</hi> giues vs warning by Oracle? Seemes he not to doe it, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3. 10. Speakes he not of an <hi>houre of temptation which ſhall come vpon all the world?</hi> Seemes not that <hi>houre</hi> to be already begunne? Surely if that Scripture looke ſo farre towards the ends of the world, and if meant of an <hi>houre of temptation,</hi> to come in this laſt houre of the world: then may we ſay of this, as our Sauiour Chriſt of that, <hi>This is the houre, and the power of darkeneſſe.</hi> The preſent troubles of the Church, may ſeeme to be the beginning of that houre. But to let this paſſe, if <hi>God</hi> warne not vs thus yet want we no warnings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If prodigious ſignes and wonders bee warnings, then judge if <hi>God</hi> haue not warned vs. Beſides that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon warning, which <hi>God</hi> gaue vs with the reſt of his Churches, in that prodigious Comet wee haue had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar warnings in this kinde. <hi>God</hi> gaue vs warning in that wonder of the doubled tydes in the riuer of <hi>Thames. God</hi> gaue vs warning in that Earth-quake March 27. 1626. <hi>God</hi> gaue vs faire warning in that prodigious ſtorme in the Citie, that fetcht the dead bodies out of their graues: together with that ſtupendious ſight vppon the water. And amongſt diuers others, I dare not ſlight that hand of <hi>God</hi> in ſending <hi>Iohn Friths preparation to the Croſſe,</hi> in the fiſh bellie to the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> a little before the Commencement. That ſuch a booke, ſhould in ſuch a manner, and to ſuch a place, and at ſuch a time be ſent: when by reaſon of peoples conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence out of all parts, notice might be giuen to all places of the land, (in my apprehenſion) it can bee conſtrued for no leſſe; then a diuine warning, and to haue this voyce with it, <hi>England prepare for the Croſſe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y with a litle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hange, as Aug. ſpeakes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us warning God gaue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omanes. <hi>Quod quanti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ali ſignum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>it? Quod ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oc ſignum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ntum ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>it, quantum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>alum erit il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d cuius hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>gnum fuit? Aug. de ciuit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>i lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 23.</note> 
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And how long, and how loude hath the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:190:17"/> Trumpet ſounded in our eares? Hath it not ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded like the Trumpet in Mount Sinai, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 13. 16. Haue wee not heard it <hi>very long,</hi> and <hi>exceeding loude,</hi> Haue not <hi>Gods</hi> watchmen from their watch-Towers a long while cryed as <hi>Eſay,</hi> 21. 8. <hi>A Lyon, A Lyon.</hi> Haue we not in this kinde beene warned vnto wearyſomneſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But what warnings hath <hi>God</hi> giuen vs in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, and miſeries of our neighbour, and ſiſter Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec illos natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale robur cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum facit vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere, nec nos naturae infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus vinci. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſibi aliud perſuadeat. Nemo aliud ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitretur, ſola nos morum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strorum vitia vicerunt. Salv. de prouid. l.</hi> 7. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo infirmis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus tradidit vt oſtenderet ſcilicet non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res valere ſed cauſam vt cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſceremus meritorum hoc fuiſſe non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium. Id.</hi>
               </note> Haue wee not ſeene the ſword in Commiſſion and vpon Circuit? Hath it not circuited from <hi>Bohemia</hi> to the <hi>Palatinate:</hi> from thence into other Prouinces of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and ſo vp the borders of <hi>Denmark:</hi> Haue we not ſeene a diuine hand in all the Churches loſſes, victory and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe going with the enemie: though there haue not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted equall power, and forces to match with them? Nay, to come neere home: Hath not the ſword ceazed vppon our owne armi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>? Hath it not begunne to eate Engliſh fleſh, and drinke Engliſh blood? Warnes it not vs faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is bending its courſe, and laying its roade to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs? The Lord threatens the Edomites. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 34. 6. <hi>That the ſword ſhalbe filled with blood, and bee made fat with fatneſſe:</hi> and elſe where, that it ſhalbe <hi>drunke with blood.</hi> The ſword hath beene a long while kept leane, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and thirſty, and hath not fed on our fleſh, and blood. Is it not to be feared, that now it hath got a ſmatch, it will like an hunger-ſterued wolfe, fall ſo much the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, and greedilier vpon vs? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nos non vicinos noſtros tantum ardere vidimus ſed ipſi iam ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus. Et quid hoc (pronefas) mali eſt. Arſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Arſimus &amp; tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas quibus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus non ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memus. Salv. de Prouid. l.</hi> 6.</note> Yea, doth not <hi>God</hi> hereby giue warning, that hee will prouide a more liberall feaſt for the ſword euen vnto <hi>fatneſſe</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſſe?</hi> If the ſword vppon other Nations, bee <hi>Gods</hi> warnings to vs of this Nation; then much more the ſword vppon thoſe of our owne Nation is a warning from <hi>God</hi> to vs, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendes to haue a great ſacrifice amongſt vs.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:190:18"/>
            <p n="5">5. And who is ſo blinde, as that he hath not ſeene the <hi>Moath</hi> at worke now a long while together? How hath it ſheared a ſunder the ſtrong threeds of our cloath, &amp; how is our garment become Moath-eaten? What elſe meanes the common cry, and complaint of the decay &amp; deadneſſe of trading, of the pouertie &amp; penurie of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places in the land? What hath it bin, that within theſe few yeares hath taken away ſo many braue, and worthy ſouldiers, men of note for birth, worth, skill and courage, that like thoſe <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5. 18. Would haue <hi>ieoparded their liues in the high places of the field:</hi> What I ſay hath it bin that hath by degrees picked out now one then another but the <hi>Moath</hi> ſent of <hi>God</hi> to prepare, and make way for a rending, and a ramping <hi>Lyon?</hi> As if <hi>God</hi> had ſaid, I am determined to bring a ſmarting judgement vppon <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland:</hi> but I ſee ſuch a mightie man, ſuch a man of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and skill, he will be a great hinderance to an enemie at his comming in, hee may bee a ſtop, and a rub in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies way: therefore I will take him out of the way, that ſo judgement may paſſe on ſmoothly without any checke. And when we haue heard the fame, and rumour of enemies approaching; alas what a deadly ſting hath the <hi>Hornet</hi> ſtricken into our heartes? how haue our ſelfe-condemning hearts, vnder the conſcience of our perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and nationall guilt melted like water?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, vnleſſe wee will wilfully ſhut our eyes, may we not trace <hi>God</hi> in the foote-ſteps of his departure from vs? May wee not finde him from betweene the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins, and remoued not onely to the threſhold: but in a manner to the Eaſt-gate of the houſe, as if hee had but one remoue more, to bee gone quite and cleane from vs? <hi>They haue ſeene thy goings O God, euen the goings of God my King in the Sanctuary, Pſal.</hi> 68. 24</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:190:18"/>
            <p>So may we ſee the goings of God, euen the goings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God our King from his Sanctuary. What elſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>anes the ſpread, and growth of Popery and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y? What elſe meanes the departure of our old Truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the increaſe of Arminianiſme? Shewes not this that God is at the threſhold, if not at the Eaſt gate? And what meanes the going away of our ſtrength that wee cannot doe as we were wont to doe as at other times. <hi>When Ephraim ſpake, there was trembling, but when he offended in Baal he died.</hi> Hoſ. 13. 1. <hi>Ephraim</hi> was terrible to all his neighbours about him, and who durſt budge againſt the name of <hi>Ephraim;</hi> but when <hi>Baal</hi> was come God was gone, and then euery paltry aduerſary trampled vpon him, and feared him no more then <hi>a dead man.</hi> How dreadfull hath the Engliſh name, and the Engliſh ſword beene to all our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; when <hi>England</hi> ſpake, there was trembling? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vbi nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſunt antiquae Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum opes &amp; dignitates? for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimi quondam Romani erant, nunc ſine viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Terrebant Romani veteres, nos timemus. O infaelicitates no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae! ad quae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenimus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>But Lord what ſhall I ſay,</hi> ſayes <hi>Ioſhua, when Iſrael turnes his backe vpon his enemies?</hi> And Lord what ſhall we ſay when <hi>England</hi> turnes her backe vpon her enemies? What ſhall we ſay? What can we ſay, but that God is departing from vs, and giues vs warning thereby, of fearefull afterclaps like to follow. <hi>Ichabod, Ichabod, where is the glory? The glory is departed.</hi> And it is with vs as with them: a people terrible <hi>hitherto,</hi> but not ſo now. <hi>Hitherto</hi> haue we beene terrible; but it is a ſigne the Lion is dead, when Hares inſult ouer him. Surely God giues vs warning that our ſhield is going, and that if we take not a courſe to fetch him backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſet him betweene the Cherubins, that wee are no better then bread for our enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</label> If God giue warning, men ſhould take the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:190:19"/> warning he giues. To what end are warnings giuen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if not taken. <hi>If the trumpet giue an vncertaine ſound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who ſhall prepare himſelfe to the battell?</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But when the trumpet giues a certayne ſound, then i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is time for men to looke about them. Two thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould make vs take warning.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The great danger that will follow vpon warning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neglected. Gods warnings neglected, doe but exaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perate wrath, and will make vengeance ſo much the ſmarter when it comes. See the danger of not taking warning. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 3. 4. 5. <hi>If the watchman blow the trumpet and warne the people, then whoſoeuer heares the ſound of the trumpet, and takes not warning, if the ſword come and take him away, his bloud ſhalbe vpon his owne head; he heard the ſound of the trumpet, and took not warning, his bloud ſhall bee vpon him.</hi> Calamity ſingle and alone, will prooue burden heauy enough; calamity with guilt, and iniquity vpon our heads, the guilt of the neglect of Gods warnings will prooue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity vnſupportable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The great enſuing benefit vpon warning taken. Let things be euer ſo dangerous and deſperate, yet if men would take Gods warnings, there were poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enough to ſaue all. Safety and preuention of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers lies in taking of warning. <hi>Noahs</hi> taking of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, was the <hi>ſauing of his houſe.</hi> Hee that <hi>takes war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhall deliuer his ſoule. Ezek.</hi> 33. 5. The King of <hi>Syria</hi> find many dangerous proiects againſt the King of <hi>Iſrael; Eliſha</hi> ſtill giues the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> warning of the danger. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 6. 10. The King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> took his warning, and what was the iſſue? <hi>Hee ſent to the place which the man of God had told him, and warned</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:190:19"/> 
               <hi>him of, and he ſaued himſelfe there not once nor twice.</hi> The way to ſaue our ſelues from the dangers wee are warned of, is to take Gods warnings. Looke vpon all the warnings God hath giuen vs, and conſider if it may not be ſayd of vs as of <hi>Moab.</hi> Ier. 48. 16. <hi>The ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity of Moab is neere to come, and his affliction ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth faſt.</hi> Yea conſider, if we haue not the <hi>buds</hi> of the <hi>figtree,</hi> telling vs that <hi>ſummer is nigh,</hi> and <hi>that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is neere euen at the doores.</hi> And haſtens our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and ſit we ſtill? As wee deſire to preuent the fatall ruine of this renowmed Church and Kingdome, ſo in the feare of God be wee perſwaded to take war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>But how is that to be done, wherein ſtands this taking of warning? That is now the ſecond thing in the Text. <hi>Noahs wiſedome</hi> in taking warning. God giues, and he takes warning; and that 1. in <hi>beleeuing</hi> it: 2. in <hi>fearing</hi> it: 3. in <hi>making vſe</hi> of it for ſafety.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In <hi>beleeuing</hi> it. <hi>By faith Noah &amp;c.</hi> That ſhould indeed be mens wiſedomes to take Gods warnings by <hi>beleeuing.</hi> God is to bee beleeued in his threatnings, aſwell as in his promiſes. And this was the <hi>Niniuites</hi> wiſedome. <hi>Ion.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>So the people of Niniueh beleeued God.</hi> And this is the firſt ground of ſafety. If <hi>Noah</hi> had not <hi>beleeued,</hi> he had not <hi>feared;</hi> if he had not <hi>fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> he had not <hi>prepared</hi> an Arke; if an Arke had not beene prepared he had periſhed. But now his Arke ſaues him; out of fayth and feare hee builds his Arke. And this is it God lookes for at our hands, that after ſo many warnings we ſhould beleeue him. <hi>Noah</hi> did ſo; and though hee were warned by immediate Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and in that regard had more reaſon to beleeue
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:190:20"/> then wee haue, yet againe in ſome reſpects wee hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more reaſon to beleeue then he had. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. He was warned onely once, and that an hundre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and twenty yeeres before the flood came; we reade o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no more warnings that hee had. In an hundred an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> twenty yeeres he might haue an hundred and twent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubts and queſtions in his heart, whether it ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be ſo or no. But we haue had warning vpon warning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeuerall kinds of warnings, and euery of theſe iterate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that as God ſpeakes to <hi>Moſes</hi> in that caſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4 1. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. ſo it may bee ſayd of vs. So that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> regard of the variety and frequency of our warnings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we haue more reaſon to beleeue then <hi>Noah</hi> had.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He was warned, as the text ſaith, <hi>of things as yet not ene;</hi> and yet he beleeues, there was nothing in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall courſe that preſaged the flouds. He ſees nothing till the floud begins, and yet he beleeued. Now in this regard wee haue more reaſon to beleeue than hee. He was warned of things not ſeene, but we are war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of things ſeene; we cannot ſay in this caſe as the Church complaines in another, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 9. <hi>We ſee not our ſignes:</hi> we ſee our ſignes, euen all ſignes of a flood that may be. <hi>Except ye ſee ſignes and wonders,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour in another caſe, <hi>ye will not beleeue, Ioh.</hi> 4. 48. it was ſomewhat yet, that they would beleeue then: we ſee ſignes and wonders, and yet wee beleeue not. <hi>Except I may ſee and feele,</hi> ſaith <hi>Thomas, I will not beleeue, Ioh.</hi> 20. 25. but when he did ſee and feele, he beleeued. We if we haue not loſt our ſight and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, both ſee and feele, and yet will not beleeue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The people of Nineveh beleeued God,</hi> when <hi>Ionas</hi> warned them, yet forty dayes &amp;c. The men of <hi>Nineveh</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:190:20"/> will riſe vp in iudgement againſt vs of this Nation: they had farre leſſe reaſon to beleeue than wee haue, and yet they beleeued; we haue farre more reaſon to beleeue, and yet we beleeue not. 1. They had but one witneſſe, we are compaſſed about with a cloude of witneſſes. 2. They were warned but once, we haue beene warned vnto wearineſſe. 3. They could ſee no likelihood of any ſuch ſuddaine danger, they knew of no preparations abroad; they ſee no enemies begirting their City with a ſiege, they were a ſtrong and a well prouided City; we heare and know of enemies, of potent and provoked enemies, and of their great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations. 4. They were Heathens and Idolaters that profeſſed not the name of God; we glory in our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian title and profeſſion, in our beleeuing in God. 5. They were warned onely by a ſtranger, one of a nation held in ſuſpition and ielouſie. If ſome Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard ſhould now come into <hi>England</hi> and threaten it with deſolation within forty dayes, what little regard would we giue vnto it. But we are warned and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by thoſe of our owne nation, of whoſe loue, loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and fidelity wee can make no doubt; by thoſe that pray for the welfare of the Nation, and wreſtle mightily with God for the peace of it. Here is a great deale of oddes betweene <hi>Englands</hi> and <hi>Ninevehs</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and yet <hi>Nineueh</hi> beleeued God, and wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued him not. We haue more warnings, they more fayth. The men of <hi>Nineueh</hi> will iudge this nation for their vnbeleefe.</p>
            <p>How long, and how often hath God warned vs by his Miniſters, and yet may they ſay as <hi>Iſ.</hi> 53. 1. <hi>Lord who hath beleeued our report?</hi> How truely agrees that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:190:21"/> to vs. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Behold and regard, and wonder mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellouſly, for I will worke a worke in your dayes which ye will not beleeue though it be told you.</hi> It is iuſt our caſe, though wee heare that which may make both our eares tingle, yet we will not beleeue it. It is iuſt with vs as it was in that caſe. <hi>Act.</hi> 27. 10. <hi>Paul</hi> there giues them fayre warning: <hi>Sirs, I perceiue that this voyage will be with hurt, and much dammage not onely of the lading and the ſhip, but alſo of our liues.</hi> And ſo it proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the ſequel. But <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>The Centurion beleeued the maſter and the owner of the ſhip more then thoſe things which were ſpoken by Paul.</hi> We are warned of a ſtorme, and that no ſmall tempeſt is like to lie vpon vs, and that all hope that wee ſhall be ſaued is like to be taken away, and yet for all this we are readier to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue any that will comfort vs with ſome poore ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of hope, then to beleeue Gods <hi>Pauls.</hi> Nay wee are worſe then the Centurion, for he yet beleeued the Maſter, and the owner of the ſhip, and if hee had told him of danger, hee would not haue looſed from <hi>Crete.</hi> Why now the <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Owner</hi> of the ſhip, he and not <hi>Paul</hi> alone tells vs of the danger. Our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne Lord the King in his Proclamation for the Parliament, and for the Generall Faſt, giues vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand of potent and dangerous enemies, and their preparations. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nam ita cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos ſua crimina praeceſſerant, vt nec metuerent periculum ſuum praenoſcebatur captivitas, nec formidabatur. Ablatus quippe erat à peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus timor ne poſſet eſſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tela</hi> Salv. de prouid l. 6.</note> If <hi>Paul,</hi> Gods Miniſters, will not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, yet let the <hi>Owner</hi> of the ſhip, Gods annointed, be beleeued. Faith would ſaue vs in this kinde. If the Centurion had beleeued <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 27. 21. the ſhip had beene ſaued. <hi>Sirs, ye ſhould haue hearkened vnto me, and haue gayned this harme and loſſe.</hi> They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued it at laſt, when the forepart of the ſhip ſtucke
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:190:21"/> faſt, and the hinder part was broken with the violence of the waues. It is too late to beleeue when all is loſt; it is good beleeuing when ſomewhat may bee ſaued by it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>fearing, mooued with feare.</hi> This muſt bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother point of wiſedome to take warning ſo as to feare. The warnings of wrath ſhould worke deepe impreſſions of feare in our hearts. <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>When I heard, my belly trembled, my lips quiuered at the voice, rottenneſſe entred into my bones.</hi> Am. 3. 8. <hi>The Lion hath roared, who will not feare?</hi> And v. 6. <hi>Shall the trumpet be blowne in the City, and the people not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid?</hi> And yet people are not afrayd, though their feare would much conduce to their ſafety. This is the way to be hid in the day of trouble, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 16 <hi>my bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trembled &amp;c. that I might reſt in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> And <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. 20. <hi>He that feared the word of the Lord made his ſeruants and his cattell flie into the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> and ſo they were ſaued from the ſtorme. Much might be ſayd to this point, but I muſt contract and haſten.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In <hi>making vſe</hi> of it for ſafety, and in taking a courſe for the preuention of thoſe dangers hee was warned of, <hi>prepared an Arke.</hi> And this is the ſpeciall point of wiſedome aboue the reſt. <hi>Prou.</hi> 22. 3. <hi>A wiſe man foreſeeth the euill.</hi> That indeed is ſome wiſdome, but that is not all; <hi>And he hides himſelfe.</hi> That's the ſpeciall wiſedome which takes a courſe for ſafety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt approaching euills. This is that we are to doe, and then indeed wee take Gods warnings when wee prouide for the worſt. And thus it concernes vs to do now, if euer. Doe we not ſee a flood comming? Why
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:190:22"/> then are we not at our Arkes? Why will wee wilfully periſh and caſt away our ſelues? When a flood cames, what would a man giue for an Arke then? Ah when the flood is come, what will be the miſerable madding feares of ſuch as ſhall not haue an Arke ready then? See their pitious condition, <hi>Ier.</hi> 47. 2. 3. <hi>Behold the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters riſe vp out of the North, and ſhalbe an ouerflowing flood, and ſhall ouerflow the land &amp;c. Then ſhall the men crie and the Inhabitants of the land ſhall howle &amp;c. The fathers ſhall not looke backe to their children for feebleneſſe of hands.</hi> How deepe and weighty is the oppreſſion of ſuch feares, as make parents grow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> What is to be done then for the making of an Arke? How may we prouide for future ſafety?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> For the making of an Arke and prouiding for future ſafety, there be firſt ſome things to be done <hi>by all</hi> in generall. Secondly ſome things <hi>by ſome</hi> in ſpeciall. 1. Thoſe things that are to be done <hi>by all,</hi> are two. 1. Humiliation and deepe abaſement of our ſoules vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gods threatning hand. So that here wee haue cauſe by the way to breake out into thankſgiuing, and to ſay as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7. 27. <hi>Bleſſed bee the Lord God which hath put ſuch a thing as this into the Kings heart:</hi> as to call forth the whole Land to the duties of Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation that we may yet beg for our liues. Well, If e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we will make an <hi>Arke</hi> for the land, and prouide for our ſafety, this is the firſt piece of timber that muſt be felled and ſquared for it. They bee great things that Humiliation will doe if it be done aright. Iob. 22. 29. 30. <hi>When men are caſt downe then ſhalt thou ſay, There is lifting vp, and he ſhall ſaue the humble perſon.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:190:22"/> 
               <hi>He ſhall deliuer the Iſland of the innocent.</hi> Alas, we are downe, exceedingly downe from the ancient excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of former times. How now might we recouer the ancient glory of this Iſland? Let men <hi>caſt themſelues downe</hi> this day, euen downe to the duſt, and lay their mouthes in the duſt, in the depth; a truth of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and though it were ten times lower with vs then it is, God would ſay, Behold <hi>England is caſt down, There ſhall be a lifting vp.</hi> What is our errand this day in theſe duties of humiliation, but that God would be pleaſed to take off preſent euils from vs, and that the future things might goe well with vs? And would wee now in good earneſt preuayle with God in theſe things? Humble we then our ſoules ſeriouſly this day before our God. Humiliation indeed will doe the deed. See 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 6. 7. <hi>The Princes of Iſrael, and the King humbled themſelues, and they ſaid, The Lord is righteous: And when the Lord ſaw that they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled themſelues, he ſayd, They haue humbled themſelues, therefore I will not deſtroy them &amp;c.</hi> And againe v. 12. <hi>And when he humbled himſelfe, the wrath of the Lord turned from him, that hee would not deſtroy him, and alſo in Iudah things went well.</hi> How welcome ſhould that man be vnto vs, that could put vs into a courſe that might put vs in hope that all things now ſhould <hi>goe well with vs?</hi> Loe here is a courſe will doe it. Our feares and dangers are exceeding great, but be they neuer ſo great, yet if we this day do all deepely humble &amp; afflict our ſoules, &amp; powre out broken and bleeding hearts, &amp; buckets of water before our God, I dare be the man that ſhall promiſe you hope yet of ſauing all. I dare the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier doe it, becauſe I haue a text for it. Ezr. 10. 1. 2. <hi>yet now</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:190:23"/> 
               <hi>there</hi> is hope <hi>in Iſrael concerning this thing.</hi> Now <hi>there is hope.</hi> Why now? There was praying, confeſſing, weeping, and the people <hi>wept very ſore,</hi> they <hi>wept a great weeping.</hi> Yet <hi>now,</hi> ſayes <hi>Shecaniah there is hope:</hi> as if he had ſayd, though our danger is great, yet now vpon this humiliation, there is hope all ſhall bee well. As therefore wee would this day goe home from this duty with <hi>hope,</hi> ſo doe we then to the purpoſe; Let hearts ſplit in ſunder, rend to peeces, mourning and melting hearts in confeſſion and ſupplication. Doe we as <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> did, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. 12. <hi>He humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe greatly.</hi> Great humiliation will ſend vs away with great hope.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Perſonall reformation and amendment of our owne euill wayes and prouocations. Euery ſoule this day quit his hands of his perſonall guilt. It is the wrath of God from whence all plagues and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments come. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nos coeleſtis irae ignem accendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus incendia quibus ardeamus: &amp; rectè utique quoties iſta ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la perferimus, ad nos dici illud Propheticum</hi> (<hi>Iſai.</hi> 50.) <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. Ite in flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ignis quam accendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis.</hi> Salv. de provid. lib. 8.</note> They bee our ſinnes that kindle this wrath; they be the fuell that kindle and feed this fire. The King of <hi>Nineueh</hi> ſaw this to be a ſpeciall prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſafety from threatned wrath. <hi>Ionah</hi> threatens ſpeedy wrath: he proclayms a faſt, he enioines ſtrickt abſtinence from food and apparell. Would that ſerue the turne? No, he will haue prayer alſo added thereto, and not ordinary prayer neither, but <hi>crying</hi> prayer, nor any crying praier neither, but let them <hi>crie migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily.</hi> And would this ſerue? No, hee will haue more, he will haue ſerious repentance and forſaking of ſin, and this not only of ſome few, but of all, <hi>let them turn euery one from his euill way.</hi> Now one would thinke nothing could be added to all this, and yet hee hath not done; there is one thing more behinde that makes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:190:23"/> vp all. Beſides their generall repentance, hee requires a ſpeciall perſonall reformation of their ſpeciall perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne, <hi>And from the violence that is in their hands.</hi> So well did he ſee the vanity of all the reſt without this laſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is ſomething to bee done <hi>by ſome ſpeciall perſons.</hi> And that is by you that are now met in this great and honourable Councell of the Land. You therefore that are the great Senate of the land, vpon whom our eyes and hopes next vnder God and the King are; Bee ye entreated in the bowels of the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> to take notice of Gods many warnings giuen to this Land, and ſo to take them to heart as to take a courſe for the preuention of threatned and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent euils. God giues you fayre warning of foule weather, and of a dreadfull flood, that is like not only to <hi>ouerflow and goe ouer and reach to the necke,</hi> as that <hi>Iſai</hi> 8. 8. but of a flood like <hi>Noahs,</hi> that is like to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top the higheſt hills euen many cubits. The Phariſees <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 3. were weather wiſe, <hi>It will bee foule wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to day, for the skie is red and lowring,</hi> but could not diſcerne <hi>the ſignes of the times,</hi> as the face of the skie. Caſt vp your eyes, you honourable Senate of the Land, and you ſhall ſee that foule weather is towards, <hi>for the skie is red and lowring.</hi> Ye ſhall ſee a cloud not onely as that 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18. 44. as big as <hi>a mans hand,</hi> but as <hi>v.</hi> 45. <hi>The heauens all blacke with cloudes and winde.</hi> Liſten and you ſhall heare <hi>a ſound of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of raine.</hi> Doe yee not already begin to feele the drops falling in your faces? We queſtion not but your wiſedomes diſcerne the ſignes, and the dangers of the times as well as the Phariſees did the face of the skie,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:190:24"/> and that you ſee all ſad preſages, and prognoſtications of a flood.</p>
            <p>Now then ſo many of you as God hath called to this Parliamentary ſeruice, we haue to tell you what God and this Realme and Church with the diſtreſſed parts of Chriſts Church abroad, looke for at your hands. God hath called you together to bee the publique Arke-wrights for the ſafety of this Church and ſtate. The eyes of theſe Dominions, and the weeping eyes of Gods Churches beyond the Seas are vpon you as vpon ſo many <hi>Noahs. Lamech</hi> when his ſonne was borne gaue him the name of <hi>Noah,</hi> that is, one refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing with reſt, bringing comfort and conſolation; you ſee his reaſon of the Impoſition, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 29. <hi>He called his name Noah, ſaying, This ſame ſhall comfort vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the worke and ſorrow of our hands, becauſe of the earth which the Lord hath curſed.</hi> Now this is that we all pray and hope for, that this preſent aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly may be an aſſembly of <hi>Noahs,</hi> that this Parliament may comfort vs concerning the feares and griefes of our hearts, and becauſe of the land which of late the Lord hath not bleſſed. This is that we all pray for, we all looke for. Now then if you would proue right <hi>Noahs</hi> to vs, ſuch as may bring vs conſolation, then for Chriſts ſake fall to the making of an <hi>Arke,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by make your ſelues <hi>Noahs</hi> and <hi>Barnabaſſes,</hi> the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſonnes of conſolation to this Church and State. Thinke when you ſit together in your ſolemne aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly that you heare the State and Church cry out vnto you, as once <hi>Peter</hi> did to Chriſt when the winds roſe, and the Sea grow rough, <hi>Maiſter, Maiſter ſaue me, I periſh.</hi> So thinke you heare the people crying from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:190:24"/> all the quarters of theſe Dominions, <hi>Fathers, Elders <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue vs, build vs an Arke, or elſe we ſinke, or elſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edileſſe we periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thinke as you ſit together in councell that you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare a voyce from all parts of the Land from whence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e be come, crying in your eares, Helpe, Helpe, or elſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e are all but dead men, Exod.</hi> 12. 33. Preſent vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our thoughts the ſad and diſconſolate condition of the Church beyond the Seas. Thinke you heare the ſhrikings of ſlaughtred and butchered infants dragd from their mothers breaſts to haue their braines daſht out againſt the ſtones of the ſtreets. Thinke that you heare the ſorrowfull and dolefull lamentations of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſht matrons, and defloured virgins in the bitterneſſe of their ſpirits, wringing their hands and rending the hayre from off their heads. Thinke that you heare the Church both at home and abroad, crying out vnto you, <hi>An Arke, An Arke,</hi> for Gods loue prouide vs an Arke. Improue all the wiſedome of your hearts, and all the power of your places to which God hath now called you, to ſaue vs from the rage of the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe waters. Gods watchmen haue a long time cried, <hi>a Flood, a Flood,</hi> Gods people now crie <hi>an Arke, an Arke.</hi> Now therefore in the name of God fall cloſe to the building of an Arke. <hi>Noah</hi> built an Arke but for the <hi>ſauing of his houſe,</hi> what is an houſe to a <hi>Church?</hi> to a <hi>kingdome?</hi> to <hi>many Churches?</hi> to <hi>many king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes? Noah</hi> built an Arke for the ſauing of <hi>eight per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</hi> what are eight perſons to millions and worldes of Chriſt an people that are like to periſh, and be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed by the mercileſſe enemies of Gods grace? that <hi>make a noyſe like the noyſe of the Seas, that make</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:190:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:190:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:190:26"/> 
               <hi>a ruſhing like the ruſhing of many waters, like the ruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of mighty waters. Iſ.</hi> 17. 12. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> But what courſe is to be taken, and what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be done for the building of an arke?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> I will not take vpon me to direct your wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>domes, but ſince it hath pleaſed you to call me to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeruice, giue me leaue ſo long as I keepe my ſelfe withi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the bounds of my profeſſion to aduiſe what I conceiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may make for common ſafety. If therefore you woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make an arke, 1. make choyce of <hi>good materials,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with to build.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Haue a care to goe to worke in a <hi>due manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Your <hi>Gopher</hi> wood or building materialls they be theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The publique reformation of all ſuch national<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prouocations as haue made God angry with the land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Illud magni &amp; ſingularis eſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti, non ſolum ipſum labe non pollui, ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videre etiam ne unquam alij pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luantur. Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator enim eſt quodammodo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis humanae, qui non tantum id agit ut ipſe bonus ſit; ſed effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care hoc nititur ut alij mali eſſe deſiſtitant.</hi> Salv. de provid. 7.</note> This muſt be the very keele of your arke, heere yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt begin: all arkes that want this <hi>Gopher</hi> wood i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the keele will prooue but <hi>cocke-boates.</hi> Alas, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> poore reliefe will a cocke-boat affoord in a ſtorm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when the curſt <hi>Euroclydon</hi> ſhall blow. A cocke-Boa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will neuer liue in a ſtorme. All courſes you can take for ſafety and deliuerance, publique reformation being neglected, will prooue but ſuch <hi>Arkes,</hi> as that wherein <hi>Moſes</hi> was expoſed. <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Arkes of bulruſhes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Alas, what ſuccour will an <hi>arke of bulruſhes</hi> yeeld in an vniuerſall deluge? Doe what you will, what you can, yet if this be not done, nothing is done. There be three things that conduce to publike ſafety. 1. The ioint endeuours of the Parliament in plotting, and the people in praying. 2. Warlike prouiſions and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. 3. And faſting. There is indeed much ſafety
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:190:26"/> in theſe, and yet if Reformation be neglected, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a vanity in all theſe, and no good will they doe. See <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. People may pray hard, and you may worke hard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et if no reformation no ſafety. You haue a good gale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f prayer at your backes, there is a great ſpirit of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> vp in the Land at this time; and I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aded that neu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> any Parliament in this Kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as more hartily prayed for. Beſides we doe with all thankfulneſſe acknowledge the great goodneſſe of God to vs in you being reputed as wiſe and iudicious able houſe as euer ſat. So that when we conſider the earneſt prayers of the whole kingdome, and the great wiſdome of this Honourable Senate; I confeſſe they are as <hi>a valley of Achor, a doore of hope.</hi> Hoſ. 2. 15. We haue great grounds of hope of much good. But yet neuertheleſſe let me be bold to tell you, that if there be no reformation of angring prouocations, all will come to nothing, and God will blaſt our hopes. It is much that prayer can doe; it is the locke and key of heauen, and yet it is little it will doe without reformation. It is much that wiſedome can do. The wiſedome of one wiſe man will do much. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. 14. 15. <hi>There was a little City and a few men within it, and there came a great King againſt it and beſieged it. Now there was found in it</hi> a poore wiſe man, <hi>and</hi> he by his wiſdome <hi>deliuered the City.</hi> Therefore what great things may a whole Parliament houſe of wiſe men doe? And yet neyther our prayers, nor your endeuours and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes will deliuer the land vnleſſe ſome courſe bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for reformation. It will bee no better in this caſe with vs, then it was with the mariners. <hi>Ion.</hi> 1. 4. 5. <hi>There</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:190:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:190:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:190:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:190:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:190:29"/> 
               <hi>was a mighty tempeſt in the ſea, ſo that the ſhip was li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to be broken.</hi> The mariners vſe all meanes they can ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſafety, they crie to their gods, they lighten the ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and yet all will not doe, yea after they knew the cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the tempeſt, v. 13. <hi>the men rowed hard to bring t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſhip to land, but they could not, for the ſea wrought an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was tempeſtuous againſt them.</hi> So then neither cryin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to their gods, nor caſting foorth the wares, nor row<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, nor tugging at their oares, will bring the ſhip t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> land out of the danger of the tempeſt, till <hi>Ionas</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> throwne ouer boord. And ſo ſoone as that was done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſee what followed, <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>They tooke vp Ionah, and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> him foorth into the ſea, and the ſea ceaſed from her ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging.</hi> It is ſo heere; let all the people in the Land tug and row with all their might in prayer, and doe you row with all the ſtrength of your wiſedome in your Parliamentary endeuours, yet till our <hi>Ionaſſes</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſſes</hi> the prouoking ſinnes of the Land that cauſe the ſtorme, and endanger the ſhip be caſt ouer boord, till they bee reformed, there is no hope of bringing the ſhip ſafe to land.</p>
            <p>And heere by the way let mee aduiſe euery Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment man that intends to further the worke of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and in it to prouide for the Lands ſafety, to begin firſt with the reformation of his owne perſon. The worke of reformation muſt not bee vndertaken with foule hands. God will haue no honour from guiltie hands. God ſends <hi>Moſes</hi> to doe a great ſeruice for his Church, hee goes about it with a guiltie hand, with the neglect of his childes circumciſion, therfore God would haue killed him by the way. He muſt firſt reforme his owne ſinne before hee muſt meddle with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:190:29"/> Iſraels deliuerance. And when God rayſed <hi>Gideon</hi> for the ſuccour of the afflicted ſtate of Iſrael, before hee muſt meddle with that worke, God ſets him another taske, Iudg. 6. 25. he muſt firſt downe with <hi>Baal.</hi> That which the Emperor <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> once ſpake at the councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> is a good rule here, one ſaid in the councell, <hi>Oportet reformationem incipere à Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis,</hi> meaning the Minorite Friers, To which the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror anſwered, <hi>Imo vero à Maioritis,</hi> meaning the Pope, Cardinals &amp;c. So I ſay if you will goe with a right foot to the worke of Reformation, begin it <hi>A Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioritis,</hi> that is, from your ſelues, you are are of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorites</hi> of the kingdome, begin with your ſelues, your eyes will be the clearer, and your hands the cleaner for the worke.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Warlike prouiſions and preparations will not do it without reformation. There be no ſuch traytors to the ſtrength of a land, no ſuch vnderminers and weakeners thereof as are vnreformed prouocations. It is but a folly to truſt to our ſtrength ſo long as no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Thinke vpon that Ezek. 33. 26. <hi>Ye ſtand vpon your ſword.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, It is but a folly for you ſo to doe, your ſword ſhall doe you little ſeruice. Why ſo? <hi>Ye worke Abomination, and yee defile euery one his neighbours wife, and ſhall you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the Land?</hi> Shall your ſwords keepe you in, whilſt your ſinnes caſt you out of poſſeſſion? Reformation is it muſt ſtrengthen our Arme, and ſharpen our ſword againſt our enemies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And what can doe more then faſting? and yet little ſeruice is it, it will doe without Reformation; <hi>Ier.</hi> 14. 10. 12. <hi>When they faſt I will not heare their cry.</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:190:30"/> What may the reaſon be? There was faſting without reformation <hi>v.</hi> 10. So <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7. deepe and harty was <hi>Ioſhuaes</hi> abaſement, but yet ſomewhat elſe was to bee done. <hi>Iſrael hath ſinned,</hi> v. 11. and they muſt away with the <hi>accurſed thing.</hi> There was a <hi>Babiloniſh gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in the camp. What if there had beene a Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh God? what if a Babiloniſh Idoll? what if a Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh Prieſt? what if ſwarmes and crowdes of Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh Prieſts? It is not faſting that will make a water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light Arke vnleſſe the execrable thing be remooued. Reformation muſt doe it. The way to eaſe our ſoules of all our grieuances and feares is to grieue the ſoule of God. Doe this and then there is hope of ſafetie. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 10. 16. <hi>And they put away the ſtrange Gods from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and ſerued the Lord:</hi> there was reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And ſee what followes. <hi>And his ſoule was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the miſery of Iſrael.</hi> And then God rayſes <hi>Iephthah</hi> for their deliuerance. And this is the firſt thing to be done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God we ſee is going and departing from vs. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to reduce him, and to ſet him in his primitiue ſtation betweene the two Cherubins the <hi>power</hi> and the <hi>purity</hi> of religion. If we haue ſinne amongſt vs, he is the one <hi>Arke</hi> in the world againſt a <hi>flood. His Name is a ſtrong tower</hi> for deliuerance, <hi>Prou.</hi> 18. 10. main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that tower. He is <hi>a ſtrong Hold in the day of trouble, Nah.</hi> 1. 7. make good that Hold. He is an Arke in the time of a flood. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 6. 7. <hi>In the floods of great waters they ſhall not come nigh vnto him. Thou art mine hiding place, thou ſhalt preſerue mee from trouble.</hi> Yea hee it is that can preuent the flood, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 59. 19. <hi>When the enemy ſhall come in like a flood, the</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:190:30"/> 
               <hi>ſpirit of the Lord ſhall put him to flight.</hi> Therefore as you would prouide for the ſafety of the Land, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for Gods returne and reſidence amongſt vs. Doe as the two diſciples did when Chriſt made as though he would haue gone from them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 29. <hi>They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned him ſaying, Abide with vs.</hi> The common complaint is, that Popery ſpreads, that Arminianiſme ſpreads, as theſe come in, ſo God will goe out; theſe will ſoone driue him out to mount Oliuet, take ſome courſe therefore to ſuppreſſe the growth of theſe. Let mee neuer proſper, if the State proſper vnder theſe. Keepe our old God, and our old truth, vnder which the kingdome hath enioyed ſo long and happy peace, and hath had ſo wonderfull victories and deliueran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. It will bee with new doctrines and nouell opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as it was with new Gods, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5. 8. <hi>They choſe new gods, then was warre in the gates.</hi> As ye loue your old peace, ſo maintayne, and doe your beſt to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine your old truth, the old way and the good way. The Lord is with you whileſt you are with him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That ſame is a ſpeciall peece of Arke-timber, right <hi>Gopher</hi> wood indeed to make Arkes withall, which we finde <hi>Ezr.</hi> 7. 23. <hi>Whatſoeuer is commanded by the God of heauen, let it bee diligently done for the houſe of the God of heauen; for why ſhould there bee wrath againſt the Realme of the King, and his ſonnes?</hi> The way to preuent a flood is to preuent wrath, the way to preuent wrath and keepe it from a Realme is to doe <hi>for the houſe of the God of heauen</hi> whatſoeuer is commanded. There bee three things commanded to be done for the houſe of the God of heauen.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His houſe lies waſte beyond the ſeas, miſerably
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:190:31"/> ruined. The God of heauen commands that his houſe be repayred. And God ſeemes to ſay now to you, as <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> to the Prieſts, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 12. 7. <hi>Why repaire ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not the breaches of the houſe?</hi> Whileſt Gods houſe lay waſte, there was wrath vpon the Land. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 4. 5. 6. But when once the houſe built and repayred, then <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>From this day will I bleſſe you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He commandes his houſe to be purged, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 5. Sanctifie the houſe of the Lord, and carry forth the filthineſſe out of the holy place. For this filthineſſe was the wrath of God vpon <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem, v.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He commands an able preaching Miniſtery in his houſe. In this reſpect many houſes of God in this land lay waſte. Many congregations want Preachers, many Miniſters want maintenance, and many coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Impropriatours want conſcience. They haue learned that language, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 83. 12. <hi>Let vs take to our ſelues</hi> the houſes of God <hi>in poſſeſsion.</hi> The God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen commands a preaching Miniſtery in his houſe, that cannot be had without maintenance. Denie the Leuites <hi>their portions,</hi> and the <hi>houſe of God will be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, Nehem.</hi> 13. 10. 11. And yee ſhall haue thoſe in their fields who ſhould bee in the Temple. Doe this one thing which the God of heauen commands for his houſe; and you ſhall notably prouide for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Land. Miniſters of the word are <hi>the horſemen and chariots of Iſrael:</hi> we feare enemies, <hi>Horſemen and chariots</hi> will be good defence, prouide ſtore of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and chariots. How confident was <hi>Abijah</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 13. 12. that <hi>Ieroboam</hi> ſhould not proſper in fighting againſt him? What was his ground? <hi>With vs are the Prieſts of the Lord with ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:190:31"/> 
               <hi>trumpets to crie alarme againſt you.</hi> But what ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was therein? Exceeding much, for <hi>Numb.</hi> 10. 9. <hi>And if ye goe to warre in your land againſt the enemie, then ſhall ye blow an alarme with the trumpets, and yee ſhalbe remembred before the Lord your God, And yee</hi> ſhalbe ſaued <hi>from your enemies.</hi> The trumpets of the Prieſts were as good as all the ſwords in Iſrael. Would ye ſaue vs from our enemies then? Prouide that the ſiluer trumpets may be blowne and may ſound in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pariſh of the Kingdome. No ſuch Arkes to ſaue from approaching dangers, as Pulpits well furniſht. How happy was the poore figge tree, <hi>Luc.</hi> 13. that had ſuch a dreſſer of the vineyard that could <hi>dig</hi> aſwel as <hi>beg.</hi> His <hi>mattocke</hi> kept off the <hi>axe.</hi> We are now in feares of enemies, and dangers; would we not be glad to haue our feares taken off, and to haue them be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our enemies, that they might make no war againſt vs? Heere is the way to doe it, to prouide preaching Miniſters in all places of the kingdome. Conſider ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly that paſſage of Scripture, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. 7. 8. 9. <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> ſets vp a <hi>teaching miniſtery,</hi> not only heere and there, but <hi>in all the cities</hi> of <hi>Iudah.</hi> And what was the ſequele? That <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>And the feare of the Lord fell vpon all the kingdomes of the lands that were round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout</hi> Iudah, <hi>ſo that they made no warre againſt</hi> Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat. It is worth our noting, that at the ſecond verſe of the Chapter it is ſayd that <hi>Iehoſhaphat placed forces in all the fenced cities of</hi> Iudah, <hi>and ſet garriſons in the land of</hi> Iudah. And yet thereupon it is not ſaid that the <hi>feare of the Lord fell</hi> vpon the neighbouring kingdomes; but when hee had eſtabliſhed a teaching Miniſtry, then his enemies <hi>had a feare, and made no</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:190:32"/> 
               <hi>warre.</hi> Forces and garriſons will not make a kingdome ſo dreadfull to an enemy as an able and godly preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſtry will doe. Haue a care of this, and in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this you ſhall do that which ſhall tend exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our ſafety and preſeruation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That is another good piece of timber for an Arke, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 7. 26. <hi>Whoſoeuer will not do the law of thy God, and the law of the King, let iudgement be executed ſpeedily vpon him, whether it be vnto death, or to baniſhment, or to confiſcation of goods, or to impriſonment.</hi> There is a generation that will neither doe the <hi>law of God,</hi> nor of <hi>the King;</hi> who both by the <hi>law of God,</hi> and <hi>the King,</hi> are men of death. Oh that life might be put into thoſe lawes, and iudgement might be ſpeedily execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whether vnto death &amp;c. The Romiſh Locuſts ſwarme euery where in the land, and they goe about to draw away men from obedience both to God and the King. And theſe they be whom we may thanke for the increaſe of Popery, what wonder is it that ſo many are drawne into the whores bed, when there be ſo many Panders in euery corner entiſing men to commit for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with the Romiſh ſtrumpet. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Audite &amp; vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te in ipſis vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus factis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia futurarum rerum ſigna &amp; indicia. Inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Sara afflixiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Agar ancil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, &amp; afflixit cam graviter Sara, &amp; fugit à facie eius. Ecce libera afflixit ancillam, &amp; non vocat illam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutionem Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus, ludit ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus cum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, &amp; perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem vocat. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictio iſta non vocatur perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, &amp; luſio illa vocatur perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. Quid vobis videtur fratres? Nonne intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us quid ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum ſit. Sic er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go quando vult Deus concitare poteſtates, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, adverſus diſſipatores Eccleſiae &amp;c. non mirabimur: quia Deus conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat vt à Sara verberetur A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, cognoſcat ſe Agar, &amp; ponat cervicem.</hi> Aug. in Euang. Ioan: tract. 11.</note> Lay the axe to the roote of the tree. Cleare the Kingdome of theſe frogs that come out of the mouth of the beaſt, and the falſe Prophet. Neuer thinke to haue your Arke wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-light, nor to prouide for our common ſafety till iudgement be executed vpon them. It is no cruelty to call for Iuſtice, nor perſecution to doe Iuſtice vpon ſuch, vpon whom Iuſtice being done, you may procure mercy from God vpon a whole Church and Nation. It is worth your notice that after the hanging of the ſonnes of <hi>Saul,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 14. it is ſaid, <hi>After that God</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:190:32"/> 
               <hi>was entreated for the land.</hi> The land for three yeeres had beene vnder a iudgement and there was (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe) <hi>entreating</hi> of God for the land; but when they were hanged, then God was <hi>entreated for the land,</hi> and then it went well with the land. And as God will in ſome caſes haue mercy and not ſacrifice; ſo in ſome he will haue iuſtice, and not ſacrifice. This day is a day of ſacrifice in prayer and humiliation for the ſafety of the land.</p>
            <p>Honoured in the Lord, God will haue iuſtice and not ſacrifice, <hi>Prou.</hi> 21. 3. <hi>To doe iuſtice and iudgement is more acceptable to the Lord than ſacrifice.</hi> Nay the doing of iuſtice is a ſacrifice, with the ſacrifices of your prayers and humiliations let God haue the ſacrifices of iuſtice, <hi>for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed,</hi> and for ſuch ſacrifices will be well pleaſed with the land. It was zeale yet in the <hi>Egyptians. Exod.</hi> 8. 26. <hi>Loe ſhall we ſacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians before their eyes, and will they not ſtone vs?</hi> How foule a ſhame for <hi>Iſraelites</hi> then, that they can ſuffer the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſacrifices of <hi>Egyptians,</hi> you are afraid that God may let in oppreſſing enemies vpon vs, you ſue this day for mercy to God in that thing; execute iuſtice and iudgement, and then may yee pray as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 121. <hi>I haue done iudgement and iuſtice, leaue me not to mine oppreſſors.</hi> And ſo I haue done with the materials of your Arke, the particulars whereby our ſafety may be procured.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The manner followes how yee ſhould build this Arke. That ſtands in theſe things, Goe to worke.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With a ſpirit of concord and vnitie. The Churches haue loſt too much already by diſunion.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:190:33"/> My praier and hearty deſire is that it may be with both the houſes of this preſent Aſſembly, as God promiſes to doe with the <hi>two houſes of Iſrael and Iudah,</hi> Ezek. 37. 19. <hi>that the Lord would make them one in his hand.</hi> And wee ſhall ſee elſewhere the miſchiefe of it when theſe two, were two, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11. 7. There were two ſtaues, of <hi>Beauty</hi> and of <hi>Binders.</hi> That <hi>ſtaffe of Binders</hi> was none other but the bond of vnity, by which the two houſes of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> were knit together. God breakes the <hi>ſtaffe of Binders, v.</hi> 14. and the <hi>brotherhood</hi> breakes, <note place="margin">So <hi>Iunius</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it.</note> and then <hi>v.</hi> 15. 16. followes the threatning of ſending into the land forreine and Romane Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours that ſhould eat the fleſh of the fat, and teare their clawes in pieces. See the miſchiefe of a <hi>ſpirit of peruerſities, Iſ.</hi> 19. 14. 16. 17. making way for the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Be it therefore the vtmoſt of your cares and wiſdomes to keepe the <hi>ſtaffe</hi> of <hi>Binders</hi> vnbroken. Knit together in and for God to doe him and his Church all poſſible ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Set vpon the worke with ſpeede. As Chriſt ſpake to <hi>Iudas</hi> in a caſe of taking away life, ſo I ſay to you in the caſe of ſauing the life of the ſtate. <hi>That which ye doe, doe quickly.</hi> It is high time that the Arke were already made. It will be too late to build Arkes when the waters are broke in: you had need doe in this caſe as <hi>Aaron</hi> did in that <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. 46. <hi>Goe quickly,</hi> for wrath is gone out.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Goe to worke thorowly, and ſubſtantially; make ſure worke: God bid <hi>Noah</hi> pitch his Arke within, and without. Hee beſtowed a great deale of time in building it, he made an huge veſſell, but if he had not pitcht it well within, and without hee had loſt all his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:190:33"/> coſt and labour; both his Arke and himſelfe had been caſt away. Therefore God appoints him <hi>Copher</hi> as well as <hi>Gopher;</hi> pitch, as well as Pine or Cedar trees.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Goe to worke couragiouſly. Betray not the State and Church with any carnall and baſe feares. <hi>If I be bereaued of my children I am bereaued</hi> was <hi>Iaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>bs</hi> concluſion. <hi>If I periſh, I periſh,</hi> was <hi>Eſthers</hi> reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tion. Let the ſame be yours alſo. It is better to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for a Kingdome, than with a Kingdome. If the Kingdome periſh who can hope to eſcape? If the publike wracke, who can hope to ſaue his priuate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ake? It is a folly when the whole Ship is in danger ſo to take care for ones priuate cabin, as not to put ones ſelfe in danger to ſaue the Ship. If the Ship drowne, what becomes of the cabins then? I ſay no more but as 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 11. <hi>Deale couragiouſly, and the Lord will be with the good.</hi> Thus we ſee the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls wherewith, and the manner how this ſauing Arke muſt be built. Now the Lord giue all you, our <hi>Noahs</hi> and Parliament Arke-wrights, hearts to ſay as <hi>Nebemiah</hi> ſpake of building the wall of <hi>Ieruſalem. Nehem.</hi> 2. 20. <hi>The God of heauen hee will proſper vs, therefore wee his ſeruants will ariſe and build.</hi> You his ſeruants take notice of Gods fayre warnings, take notice of our feares and dangers, take notice of the hopes and expectations of the Church at home and abroad, take notice of the eyes of the kingdome, and of all Chriſtendome that are vpon you, <hi>Doe you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and build, and the God of heauen proſper you.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
